Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Learning Resource Center/Eckles Library Collection, 1963-1988 MVC0030.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Learning Resource Center/Eckles Library Collection
1963-1988
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0030.RG
8 Linear Feet 16 document boxes
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875 and a two year junior college was added in 1927. The Junior College remained open until 1969, when Mount Vernon College became a four-year unversity. The university was an independent institution until 1999, when it became affilated with The George Washington University. This collection includes files related to the Library Resource Center at Mount Vernon College as well as materials related to the planning and construction of Eckles Library, which was built between 1986 and 1987.
Conditions Governing Access
Some material in Series 3 of this collection is restricted. See Special Collections staff for assistance. Special Collections staff will work with GW Counsel's office to determine access.
Arrangement
Arranged into four series: Library Director Lucy Cocke's files, Learning Resource Center files, Library studies, plans, and contracts, and Photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. Collection transferred to Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials related to the construction of Eckles Library at Mount Vernon College, materials regarding the library belonging to library director Lucy Coke, materials from the Library Resource Center, and photographs of the library during and after construction. The material dates from 1963-1988.
Biographical / Historical
Eckles Library was constructed between 1986 and 1987. Funding for the library was initiated by a bequest from Charles Eckles to Mount Vernon College. The library was dedicated on September 18, 1987.
The Mount Vernon Seminary began in 1875 as a private high school and junior college for women, founded by Elizabeth J. Somers. The George Washington University initially affiliated with Mount Vernon College, and ultimately acquired the college's property and legacy in 1999.
The first school of higher education available to women in Washington, D.C., Mount Vernon Seminary and College had five different locations throughout its history:
1875-1880: Elizabeth Somers began tutoring the young daughters of prominent Washington men in her home at 204 F Street, NW in Washington, DC.
1880-1917: The school moved to 1100 M Street, NW where it expanded rapidly to include three additional houses, a courtyard, tennis court, and basketball court.
1917-1942: Having outgrown its M Street location, the school moved to a 15-acre campus on Nebraska Avenue, NW. In 1942, the United States Navy took over the Nebraska Avenue campus to use its facilities for the war effort.
1943-1946: The school resumed courses in February 1943 at the top floor of a Garfinckel's department store building in the Spring Valley neighborhood of Washington, D.C.
1946-1999: Between 1944 and 1946, the school built a new 21-acre campus located on Foxhall Road in Washington, D.C. using money granted to the college by the United States Navy in compensation for the military takeover of its property.
The last Seminary class graduated in 1969, and the school was then officially renamed to Mount Vernon Junior College. In 1976, Mount Vernon College became an accredited four year college. In 1997, the Board of Trustees decided that the College would close as an independent institution. As of June 30, 1999, Mount Vernon became affiliated with The George Washington University.
Building construction; Libraries; Women -- Education; Mount Vernon College
- Library Director Lucy Cocke's files, 1963-1987; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials belonging to Library Director Lucy Cocke concerning the design and construction of Eckles Library. The materials include correspondence with architects, design research, and photographs. The materials in this series date from 1963-1987.
  - Academic library building in... by Jerrold Orne, 1967-1976; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Academic library statistics, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Institute of Architects files, 1984; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Architect selection, 1973; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Architectural portfolio special issue, 1983; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Books, libraries, and electronics essays, 1982; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Budget preparations, 1984; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Building and remodling libraries, The Homestead, Hot Springs, VA, 1983; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Building consultants, 1983; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Building plans, 1983; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Building program statement, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with library staff, 1984-1985; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ceder Crest and Muhlenberg College library plan, 1983-1984; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence with potential architects, 1982; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with constultants, 1983-1984; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cover letters/resumes from catalogue librarian applicants, 1987; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Design research, 1976-1984; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Design research, 1980-1983; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Design research, 1981; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Design research, 1982-1983; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Design research, 1983-1984; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Education building library University of Arkansas photos, 1982; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Eggers Group P.C. Architects portfolios, 1984; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Ellen and Alvin Aisenberg Collection: a bibliography, 1982; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Faulkner Design Inc. architect proposal, 1984; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Floor plans and drawings, 1984; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Geddes, Brecher, Qualls, Cunningham portfolio, 1984; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Geddes, Brecher, Qualls, Cunningham portfolios, circa 1983; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Geddes, Brecher, Qualls, Cunningham portfolios, circa 1983; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Georgetown new library plans, 1965; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Georgetown University library handicapped services, 1982; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hot Springs conference, 1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Howard University library plan, 1976; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Initial correspondence with prospective architects, 1984; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Journal articles about library design, circa 1960-1969; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Library building program statements with reviewer comments, 1984; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Library design, 1981; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Library Issues - September, 1983; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lighting renovation files, 1986-1987; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Library research and statistics, 1981; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Loyola/Notre Dame library audiovisual center, 1983; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Media center facilities design, ALA, 1978; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Meeting with faculty March 18, 1983; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Memoranda from Perkins & Will, 1987; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Mount Vernon College design and construction schedule, 1983; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Mount Vernon College library proposed blueprints, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Notes for library planning task force meeting, 1983; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Notes for meetings, 1984; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Oregon Institute of Technology photos, 1982; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Planning and design for library buildings, 1977; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Planning the college library building, Frazer Poole, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Priorities for academic libraries, Galvin and Lynch, 1982; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Projections, 1982; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Ramapo College, Mahwah, NJ photos and plans, 1982; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Recommended architects, 1984; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Sagetn - Webster - Crenshaw - Foley New York photos and blue prints, 1982; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - St. Mary's College library, Indiana plans and photos, 1982; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Standards for college libraries, 1979-1983; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Supplies account, 1978-1979; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Trinity College library plan, 1963; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Two year college libraries newspaper articles, circa 1977; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - University of Texas - Austin library photos, 1982; Series 1 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Washington and Lee new library plan, 1971; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Learning Resource Center files, 1968-1982; Series 2
  This materials in this series include financial accounts information and administrative files concerning the Learning Resource Center. The materials date from 1968-1982.
  - Accounts, 1977-1978; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Accounts, 1977-1978; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Accounts, 1977-1978; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Budget and renovation proposals, 1973-1975; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Circulation statistical report, 1976-1977; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Friends of the library, 1982; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Library Resource Center publications, circa 1972-1975; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Library Resource Center statistics, reports, holdings, acquisition, and inhouse, 1970-1971; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Materials orders, 1976; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Materials orders, 1976-1977; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Materials orders, 1977; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Materials orders, 1978; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Microfilm account and orders, 1978-1979; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Middle States Association/evaluation report, 1968; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Library Resource Center files, 1975; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Periodicals account and orders, 1975-1976; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Periodicals account and orders, 1975-1976; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Periodicals account and orders, 1980-1981; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Repairs account, 1976-1980; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Supplies account, 1976-1977; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Supplies account, 1976-1977; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Supplies account, 1979-1980; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Supplies before June 1978, 1977-1978; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Title II periodicals account and order, 1975-1976; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Library studies, plans, and contracts, 1968-1988; Series 3
  Conditions Governing Access
  Some material in this series is restricted. See Special Collections staff for assistance. Special Collections staff will work with GW Counsel's office to determine access.
  This series includes materials related to the design and construction of Eckles Library. The materials include drawings, project propsals, architects' correspondence, legal counsel, product specifications, etc. The materials date from 1968-1988.
  - American Institute of Architects contract, 1986; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Architects' correspondence, 1987-1988; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Bills, part 1, 1984-1987; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Bills, part 2, 1984-1987; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Binder, named gifts, photos, study rooms plans, furniture, 1987; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Building permit (library), 1986; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Building program for Library Communications Center, 1984; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Building program for Library Communications Center, 1984; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Computers, 1985-1986; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Construction and architect contact log, undated; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (incoming), 1985; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Dormitory, 1969-1971; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Ellis, Reed; De Maria, Ellis and Hunt, 1981-1984; Series 3 (Box R1, Folder 1, Box 7, Folder 11)
    General
    Please note: the contents of this file are restricted. Please contact Special Collections staff for more information.
  - Elevator files - Dover Elevator Company, 1988; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Equipment - kitchen, undated; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Furniture invoices, 1987; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Geotechnical Engineering Services, 1985; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Hogan and Hartson, 1986; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 2, Box R1)
  - Hogan and Hartson (Claire Guthrie), 1984-1987; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 3, Box R1)
  - Hogan and Hartson correspondence, 1985; Series 3 (Box R1, Folder 4, Box 8)
  - In-house memoranda, 1985-1986; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - J. Lee Donnelly & Son, Inc. (library planning), 1985; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Jane Evans binder, "Library" part 1, 1985; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Jane Evans binder, "Library" part 2, 1985; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Jane Evans binder, "Library" part 3, 1985-1986; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Kindell, 1987; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Library architecht fees, 1984-1985; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Libary building budget, 1986; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Library building plans, 1985-1986; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Library building program, 1984; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Library committee, 1984; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Library construction documents part 1, circa 1984; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Library construction documents part 2, circa 1984; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Library financial services, 1984-1985; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Library list of contacts, undated; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Library memorandum, 1985-1986; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Library planning committee, 1984; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Library planning committee, 1984; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Loose construction and maintenance files, 1986-1987; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Loose construction and maintenance files, 1986-1987; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Loose construction and maintenance files, 1987-1988; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1985; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous construction correspondence, 1986; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - MNH Applied Electronics, 1984-1985; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Mount Vernon College conceptual budget, 1985; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Mount Vernon College library groundbreaking and dedication, 1984-1987; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Mount Vernon College library proposed conceptual design, undated; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Mount Vernon College library new library binder part 1, 1985; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Mount Vernon College library new library binder part 2, 1985; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Mount Vernon College Signal Construction Corp., 1986; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Mount Vernon Junior College self-evaluation study for Middle States, 1968; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - National Trust for Historic Preservation reproduction furniture, 1987-1988; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Perkins & Will correspondence, 1985-1987; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 4, Box R1, Folder 5)
  - Perkins & Will letters of transmittal, 1986; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Perkins & Will letters of transmittal, 1986; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Perkins & Will letters of transmittal, 1986; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Perkins & Will letters of transmittal, 1986-1987; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Perkins & Will letters of transmittal, 1986-1987; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Perkins & Will letters of transmittal, 1986-1987; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Perkins & Will letters of transmittal, 1986-1987; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Perkins & Will letters of transmittal, 1986; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Perkins & Will letters of transmittal, 1986-1987; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Perkins & Will sprinkler system drawings, 1987; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Project manual for Mount Vernon College library part 1, 1986; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Project manual for Mount Vernon College library part 2, 1986; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Project manual for Mount Vernon College library part 3, 1986; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Project manual for Mount Vernon College library, general furnishings, 1987; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Project manual, steel shelving, shelving correspondence, 1987-1988; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Proposed interior furnishings Mount Vernon College library, 1986-1987; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Signage specifications, project manual for Mount Vernon College library, 1987; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Topographical survey, 1985; Series 3 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Wilkes, Artis, Hendrick & Lane, 1986; Series 3 (Box R1, Folder 5, Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Construction plans, 1986; Series 3 (Box 15, Folder 13)
- Photographs, 1985-1987; Series 4
  This series contains photographs from the construction and dedication ceremony of Eckles Library. The materials date from 1985-1987.
  - Miscellaneous photos, circa 1985-1987; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Mount Vernon College library construction photos, 1986-1987; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Mount Vernon College library construction photos, 1986-1987; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Mount Vernon College library construction/dedication photos, 1986-1987; Series 4 (Box 14, Folder 7)